<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" status="draft">
    <title>OpenStack API Extensions</title>
    <subtitle>An Overview</subtitle>
    <info>
        <copyright>
            <year>2010</year>
            <year>2011</year>
            <holder>Rackspace US, Inc.</holder>
        </copyright>
        <pubdate>2011-06-10</pubdate>
        <legalnotice role="apache2">
            <annotation>
                <remark>Copyright details are filled in by the template.</remark>
            </annotation>
        </legalnotice>
        <abstract>
            <para>
                This document provides an overview of the OpenStack API extension
                mechanism.
            </para>
        </abstract>
    </info>
    <chapter version="5.0" xml:base="chapters/overview.xml">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
        The OpenStack extension mechanism makes it possible to add
        functionality to OpenStack APIs in a manner that ensures
        compatibility with existing clients. This capability
        allows OpenStack operators and vendors to provide
        innovative functionality to their clients and provides a
        means by which new features may be considered in upcoming
        versions of OpenStack APIs.
    </para>
    <para>
        This document describes the extension mechanism in detail.
        It provides guidance to API implementors and clients on
        developing and consuming API extensions, it describes the
        rules by which extensions are governed, and it describes
        the process used to promote API extensions to new features.
    </para>
    <warning security="draft">
        <para>Please note that this document is a <emphasis role="strong">draft</emphasis>. It
            is intended to give developers an opportunity to provide feedback. If you begin
            implementing against this early access specification, please recognize that it is
            still subject to change. Comments, feedback, and bug reports are always welcomed;
            please submit these in the webhelp discussion forum at: <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/">http://docs.openstack.org/</link>.</para>
    </warning>
    <section>
        <title>Intended Audience</title>
        <para>This document is intended for software developers who wish either to implement or
            to consume an extendable OpenStack API. It assumes that the reader has a general
            understanding of:</para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para>ReSTful web services</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>HTTP/1.1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>JSON and/or XML data serialization formats</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>At least one OpenStack API: Compute,
                    Object Storage, etc.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Organization of this Document</title>
        <variablelist spacing="normal">
            <?dbfo list-presentation="blocks"?>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="Background"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Provides background information on
                        OpenStack extensions and the OpenStack
                        extension mechanism.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><phrase security="draft">Chapter 3, <firstterm>Extensions and ReST</firstterm></phrase></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Describes the specifics of implementing
                        and consuming extensions in ReST APIs.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><phrase security="draft">Chapter 4, <firstterm>Extension Governance and Promotion</firstterm></phrase></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Describes API governance and the process
                        by which extensions can be promoted to new
                        features in future revisions of an API.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><phrase security="draft">Chapter 5, <firstterm>Summary</firstterm></phrase></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Briefly summarizes the benefits of the extension mechanism and
                        provides a brief overview of how extensions are used.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Document Change History</title>
        <informaltable rules="all">
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td align="center" colspan="1">Revision Date</td>
                    <td align="center" colspan="4">Summary of Changes</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td colspan="1" align="center">June 10, 2011</td>
                    <td colspan="4">
                        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Initial draft.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </informaltable>
    </section>
</chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="Background" version="5.0" xml:base="chapters/background.xml">
        <title>Background</title>
        <para>
            This chapter provides background information on OpenStack
            extensions and the OpenStack extension mechanism.  It
            describes what extensions are, how the extension mechanism
            in OpenStack is related to the OpenGL extension mechanism,
            the differences between extensions and versions, the
            concept of versioning extensions, and why extensions are
            vital when defining a pluggable architecture.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>What are Extensions?</title>
            <para>
                OpenStack APIs are defined strictly in two forms: a
                human-readable specification (usually in the form of a
                developer's guide) and a machine-processable
                WADL. These specifications define the core actions,
                capabilities, and media-types of the API. A client can
                always depend on the availability of this
                <firstterm>core API</firstterm> and implementers are
                always required to support it in its entirety.  Requiring strict adherence to the
                core API allows clients to rely upon a minimal level
                of functionality when interacting with multiple
                implementations of the same API.
            </para>
            <para>
                Note that it is quite possible that distinct
                implementations of an OpenStack API exist. First
                because API specifications are released under a free
                license, so anyone may use them to implement a core
                API. Furthermore, the OpenStack implementations
                themselves are released under a free license, making
                it possible to alter the code to create a specialized
                version. Such a specialized implementation could
                remain OpenStack-compatible even if it were to
                implement new features or add new capabilities, but
                only if it made the changes in a manner that ensures
                that a client expecting a core API would continue to
                function normally — this is where extensions
                come in.
            </para>
            <para>An <firstterm>extension</firstterm> adds capabilities to an API beyond those
                defined in the core. The introduction of new features, MIME types, actions, states,
                headers, parameters, and resources can all be accomplished by means of extensions to
                the core API. In order for extensions to work, the core API must be written in such
                a manner that it allows for extensibility. Additionally, care should be taken to
                ensure that extensions defined by different implementers don't clash with one
                another, that clients can detect the presence of extensions via a standard method,
                and that there is a clear promotion path at the end of which an extension may become
                part of a future version of the core API. These actions, rules, and processes
                together form the <firstterm>extension mechanism</firstterm>. It is important that
                core APIs adhere to this mechanism in order to ensure compatibility as new
                extensions are defined. Note also that while a core API may be written to allow for
                extensibility, the extensions themselves are never part of the core.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Relationship to OpenGL</title>
            <para>
                In the 1990s, OpenGL was developed as a portable open
                graphics library standard.  The goal was to provide a
                cross-platform library that could enable developers to
                produce 3D graphics at real time speeds (30-120 frames
                per second). There were several major challenges to
                meeting this goal. In order to be considered an open
                standard, control needed to shift from Silicon
                Graphics (SGI), who originally developed OpenGL, to an
                independent Architecture Review Board (ARB) who would
                be responsible for approving specification changes,
                marking new releases, and ensuring conformance
                testing. Additionally, the graphics library itself
                would need to be designed in a manner that would allow
                the establishment of a stable and portable platform
                for developers. Finally, the library would need to
                garner the support of graphics hardware vendors as
                they would be providing the hardware acceleration
                needed to meet the goal of performing at real-time
                speeds.
            </para>
            <para>Gaining vendor support is challenging because vendors are often in direct
                competition with one another. They differentiate themselves by creating innovative
                new features and by providing niche functionality to their users. Thus, OpenGL was
                faced with two competing requirements. On the one hand, it needed to abstract away
                vendor differences in order to provide a stable cross-platform environment to
                developers. On the other hand, in order to garner vendor support, it needed a method
                by which vendors could differentiate themselves and provide innovative new features
                and niche functionality to their users.</para>
            <para>The OpenGL extension mechanism was developed to solve these problems. The
                extension mechanism achieved balance between the two requirements by maintaining the
                core specification under the direction of the Architecture Review Board while
                allowing vendors to define extensions to the core OpenGL specification. The core
                specification remained uncluttered and presented a unified view of common
                functionality. Because extensions were detectable at run time, developers could
                write portable applications that could adapt to the hardware on which they were
                running. This method of allowing for an extensible API has proven to be a very
                successful strategy. More than 500 extensions have been defined in OpenGL's lifetime
                and many vendors, including NVidia, ATI, Apple, IBM, and Intel, have participated in
                the process by developing their own custom extensions. Additionally, many key
                innovations (such as vertex and fragment shaders) have been developed via the
                extension process and are now part of the core OpenGL API.</para>
            <para>OpenStack, while very different from OpenGL, shares many similar goals and faces
                many of the same challenges. OpenStack APIs are designed to be open API standards.
                An important goal is to provide developers with a ubiquitous, stable, any-scale
                cloud development platform that abstracts away many of the differences between
                hosting providers and their underlying infrastructure (hypervisors, load balancers,
                etc.). A Policy Review Board, similar to OpenGL's Architecture Review Board, is
                responsible for  directing development of these APIs in a manner that ensures these
                goals are met. As with OpenGL, OpenStack requires support from vendors (and cloud
                providers) in order to be successful. As a result, OpenStack APIs also aim to
                provide vendors with a platform which allows them to differentiate themselves by
                providing innovative new features and niche functionality to their users. Because of
                these similarities, the OpenStack extension mechanism described in this document is
                modeled after the OpenGL extension mechanism. The methods by which extensions are
                defined vary drastically, of course, since the nature of the APIs is very different
                (C versus ReST); however, the manner in which extensions are documented, the way in
                which vendors are attributed, and the promotion path that an extension follows, all
                borrow heavily from OpenGL.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Extensions and Versions</title>
            <para>Extensions are always interpreted in relation to a version of the core API. In
                other words, from a client's perspective, an extension modifies <emphasis>a
                    particular version</emphasis> of the core API in some way. In reality, an
                extension may be applicable to several versions of an API at once. For example, a
                particular extension may continue to be available as a core API moves from one
                version to another. In fact, different implementations may decide to include support
                for an extension at different versions. As explained in
                <phrase security="draft">the chapter on "Extension Governance and Promotion"</phrase>,
                when an extension is defined, the minimal version of the core API that is required
                to run the extension is specified; implementers are free to support the extension in
                that version or in a later version of the core. Note, however, that because the
                extension mechanism allows for promotion, an extension in one version of a core API
                may become a standard feature in a later version.</para>
            <note>
                <para>
                    As always, implementers are not required to
                    support an extension unless it is promoted to the
                    core.
                </para>
            </note>
            <para>Because several versions of the core API may be supported simultaneously, and
                because each version may offer support for a different set of extensions, clients
                must be able to detect what versions and extensions are available in a particular
                deployment. Thus, both extensions and versions are queryable. Issuing a <command>GET</command> on the
                base URL (<code>/</code>) of the API endpoint returns information about what
                versions are available. Similarly, issuing a <command>GET</command> on the API's extensions resource
                    (<code>/v1.1/extensions</code>) returns information about what extensions are
                available. (See
                <phrase security="draft">the chapter on "Extensions and ReST"</phrase>
                for details of such requests.) Note that,
                since extensions modify a particular version of the API, the <code>extensions</code>
                resource itself is always accessed at a particular version.</para>
            <para>Backward-compatible changes in an API usually require a minor version bump. In an
                extensible API, however, these changes can be brought in as extensions. The net
                effect is that versions change infrequently and thus provide a stable platform on
                which to develop. The Policy Review Board (PRB), with the help of project team
                leaders, is responsible for ensuring that this stability is maintained by closely
                guarding core API versions. Extensions, however, can be developed without the
                consent or approval of the PRB. They can be developed in a completely decentralized
                manner both by individual OpenStack developers and by commercial vendors. Because
                extensions can be promoted to standard features, the development of new versions can
                be influenced significantly by individual developers and the OpenStack client
                community and is therefore not strictly defined by the PRB. In other words, new
                features of a core API may be developed in a bottom-up fashion.</para>
            <para>
                That said, not all extensions are destined to be
                promoted to the next API version. Core APIs always
                deals with core functionality — functionality
                that is supported by all implementations and is
                applicable in common cases.  Extensions that deal with
                niche functionality should always remain extensions.
            </para>
            <para>
                The table below summarizes the differences between
                versions and extensions.
            </para>
            <table frame="all">
                <title>Versions versus Extensions</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Versions</entry>
                            <entry>Extensions</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>Rare</title>
                                    <para>
                                        Versions provide a stable
                                        platform on which to develop.
                                    </para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>Frequent</title>
                                    <para>
                                        Extensions bring new features
                                        to the market quickly and in a
                                        compatible manner.
                                    </para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>Centralized</title>
                                    <para>
                                        Versions are maintained by the
                                        entity that controls the API
                                        Spec: the OpenStack Policy
                                        Review Board. Only the PRB can
                                        create a new version; only the
                                        PRB defines what "OpenStack
                                        Compute 1.1" means.
                                    </para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>Decentralized</title>
                                    <para>
                                        Extensions are maintained by
                                        third parties, including
                                        individual OpenStack
                                        developers and software
                                        vendors. Anyone can create an
                                        extension.
                                    </para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>Core</title>
                                    <para>
                                        Versions support core
                                        functionality.
                                    </para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>Niche</title>
                                    <para>
                                        Extensions provide specialized
                                        functionality.
                                    </para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>Queryable</title>
                                    <para>
                                        Issuing a <command>GET</command> on the base
                                        URL (<code>/</code>) of the
                                        API endpoint returns
                                        information about what
                                        versions are available.
                                    </para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>Queryable</title>
                                    <para>
                                        Issuing a <command>GET</command> on the API's
                                        extensions resource
                                        (<code>/v1.1/extensions</code>)
                                        returns information about what
                                        extensions are available.
                                    </para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Versioning Extensions</title>
            <para>There is no explicit versioning mechanism for extensions. Nonetheless, there may
                be cases in which a developer decides to update an extension after the extension has
                been released and client support for the extension has been established. In these
                cases, it is recommended that a new extension be created. The extension may have a
                name that signifies its relationship to the previous version. For example, a
                developer may append an integer to the extension name to signify that one extension
                updates another: <code>RAX-PIE2</code> updates <code>RAX-PIE</code>.</para>
            <para>Extensions may have dependencies on other extensions. For example,
                    <code>RAX-PIE2</code> may depend on <code>RAX-PIE</code> and may simply add
                additional capabilities to it. In general, dependencies of this kind are discouraged
                and implementers should strive to keep extensions independent. That said, extension
                dependencies allow for the possibility of providing updates to existing extensions
                even if the original extension is under the control of a different vendor. This is
                particularly useful in cases where an existing extension has good client support.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Extensions and Pluggability</title>
            <para>Core APIs abstract away vendor differences in order to provide a cross-platform
                environment to their clients. For example, a client should be able to interact with
                an OpenStack load balancing service without worrying about whether the deployment
                utilizes Zeus, Pound, or HAProxy on the backend. OpenStack implementations strive to
                support multiple backends out of the box. They do so by employing software drivers.
                Each driver is responsible for communicating to a specific backend and is in charge
                of translating core API requests to it.</para>
            <para>The core API contains only those capabilities which are applicable to all
                backends; however, not all backends are created equal, with each backend offering a
                distinct set of capabilities. Extensions play a critical role in exposing these
                capabilities to clients. This is illustrated below. Here, extensions fill in the gap
                between the common capabilities that the core API provides and the unique
                capabilities of the Zeus load balancer. In a sense, one can think of extensions as
                providing frontends to OpenStack plug-ins.</para>
            <figure xml:id="core-extensions">
                <title>Extensions and Pluggability</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="fo">
                        <imagedata scale="100" fileref="../figures/apix-1service-core-extensions-manybackends.svg" format="SVG" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata fileref="../figures/apix-1service-core-extensions-manybackends.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
